[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Twenty-eight]
[第二十八集]
Please be quiet.
大家请安静
Quiet please
请安静
Mr Cai has arrived.
蔡先生到了
Mr. Cai, classmates
蔡先生 同学们
Take to the streets today.
今天上街游行
It was the collective decision of all of us.
是我们所有人集体的决定 大
So this consequence
所以这个后果
Can't let the arrested 32 classmates
不能让那被捕的三十二名同学
To undertake
来承担
I propose
我提议
All our classmates in Peking University
我们北大所有的同学
draw together
团结起来
Turn yourself in at the door of the army commander.
团起来
Respect prison
尊监狱
Pledge to defend our arrested classmates to the death
誓死保卫我们被捕的同学
Vow to advance and retreat with the arrested classmates
誓与被捕同学同进退
Let's be quiet first.
大家先安静一下
Let's listen to Mr Cai.
我们听蔡先生讲话
I want to tell you.
我想告诉大家
The more you encounter this situation.
越是遇到现在这个情况
The more we need to calm down.
我们越需要冷静
We are all scholars.
我们都是读书人
We are sensible.
我们是明事理的
We are rational.
我们是理智的
We will never do it.
我们绝不会做
That kind of mob thing
那种乌合之众的事情
Students' patriotic actions
同学们的爱国行动
I Cai Yuanpei support it.
我蔡元培是支持的
But this happened.
但是出现了这个情况
Out of my expectation.
出乎我的预料
I am very sad.
我非常痛心
Very sad
非常痛心
For this reason, I am the principal
为此我这个当校长的
To resign
要引辞职
Take the blame and resign
要引咎辞职
But the most urgent thing now
但是现在当务之急的
Is to do everything possible.
是要想尽一切办法
To rescue the arrested 32 students.
去营救被捕的三十二名同学
I want them to come out safely.
我要让他们安全地出来
I just got word that
我刚刚得到消息说
Our arrested classmate
我们的被捕的同学
Has been transferred to the metropolitan police department.
已经转移到京师警察厅了
I don't know whether you are worried or happy.
是忧是喜 我不清楚
But I made up my mind.
但是我下定决心
I want to go to the Metropolitan Police Department in person.
我要亲自到京师警察厅
Go to police chief Wu Bingxiang.
去找警察总监吴炳湘
I want someone from him.
我要向他要人
I'm going to take my classmates
我要把我的同学
Bring it back to school safely.
平安地带回学校来
I ask my classmates to be patient at school.
我请同学们在学校 耐下心来
Don't go out.
不要出去
Listen to my news.
听我的消息
Can everyone do it?
大家能做到吗
can
能
classmates
同学们
What Mr. Cai said just now
蔡先生刚才那番话
Is everyone listening?
大家听进去了吗
We are going to make a
我们是要做一个
A patriotic Chinese.
有爱国心的中国人
But patriotic.
但是爱国
We need to calm down even more.
我们更需要冷静冷静
calm
冷静
okay
好吗
nicely
好好
This meeting unanimously decided that
本次会议一致决定
Closed Peking University
封闭北京大学
Replace the president of Peking University
撤换北大校长
And severely deal with the arrested students.
和严厉处置被捕学生
Instruct Wu Bingxiang, director of the Metropolitan Police Department.
责成京师警察厅总监吴炳湘
Put forward the disposal plan for the arrested students.
负责提出对被捕学生的处置方案
Instruct Wu Bingxiang Chen Zhuan Fu Zengxiang
责成吴炳湘 陈篆 傅增湘
Responsible for stopping May 7th
负责阻止五月七日
The National Convention held in Central Park
在中央公园召开的国民大会
Instruct the Ministry of Education
责成教育部
Responsible for restoring school order.
负责恢复各学校秩序
This meeting is over.
本次会议结束
the meeting is over
散会
Brother Cheng, I want to resign.
丞兄 我要辞职
This errand
这个差事
I really can't go on.
我实在是于不下去了
Uncle took the lead in the national disaster and left.
叔 国难当头一走了之
This is not your style.
这可不是你的风格呀
I don't go.
我不走
What can I do without leaving?
我不走又能做什么
The student parade was driven by patriotism.
学生游行是受爱国心所驱使
But any sensible person can see it.
但凡是个明白人都看得出来
You arrested so many students.
你们抓了那么多的学生
Also close Peking University and replace Cai Heqing.
还要封闭北大 撤换蔡鹤卿
This will not only discourage students.
这样做不但劝不了学生
Instead, it will add fuel to the fire
反而会火上浇油
It is bound to lead to greater turmoil.
势必引发更大的动荡
I can't follow you to this muddy water.
我不能跟着你们去躁这个浑水
Yuan Shu lai lai lai
沅叔来来来
Uncle lai lai lai
又来来来
Come on
来嘛
You really don't understand my mind?
我的心思你真的不明百吗
My idea is the same as yours.
我的想法跟你是一样的
But have you ever been to Duan Qirui?
可是你得过段祺瑞吗
Students burn Zhao Jialou.
学生火烧赵家楼
Wound Zhang Zongxiang
打伤了章宗祥
Xu Shuzheng threatened to set up a cannon on Jingshan.
徐树铮扬言要在景山上架起大炮
Raze Peking University to the ground.
把北大夷为平地
under the circumstances
在这种情况下
Don't you come up with some measures?
你不拿出几条措施来
Have to explain the past?
交代得过去吗
You withdrew Cai Yuanpei.
你们撤了蔡元培
Who will be the president of Peking University?
准备让谁来当北大校长
Duan Qirui nominated Ma Qichang.
段祺瑞提名马其昶
I was prevaricated.
被我塘塞过去了
Make a gesture first.
先做个姿态
Let's talk about it when things calm down.
把事态平息了再说
Now this Peking University
眼下这个北大呀
I think except Cai Yuanpei
我看除了蔡元培
No one can control it.
谁也掌控不了
Now the question is
现在的问题是
The police arrested dozens of students.
警察厅抓了几十个学生
This is the curse.
这就是祸根哦
If they don't play it or something goes wrong
如果他们不放或者出了什么问题
Then this will be a big deal.
那这事就闹大了
We can't afford it.
咱们谁也担待不起呀
Student affairs are very difficult.
学生的事很棘手
The well-being people unanimously demanded severe punishment.
安福系的人一致要求严惩
Only this Wu Bingxiang is smart.
只有这个吴炳湘还算聪明
He intends to make use of these students.
他打算利用这批学生
As Cai Yuanpei
作为制蔡元培
And disintegration of students.
和瓦解学生的工具
And I hope I can fully cooperate with him.
并且希望我全力配合他
This Wu Bingxiang
这个吴炳湘
But Duan Qirui's clique!
可是段祺瑞的嫡系呀
You can trust him.
你能信任他
He is also responsible.
他也是职责所系
To maintain public order in the capital.
要维系京师治安
Then you can't offend students.
那就不能得罪学生
Things are going to be big.
事情要大了
He was the first to be held accountable.
第一个被问责的就是他
I look!
我看哪
But it's hanging by a thread.
这事可是悬得很
It's like walking a tightrope.
像是在走钢丝啊
Be reluctant.
勉为其难吧
Big deal.
大不了啊
I resign with you.
我跟你一起辞职
These students
这些学生啊
That's making trouble for bad friends.
那就是为非作友 寻滋事
You have to catch what you should catch.
该抓的就得抓
Scratch, scratch, and you'll know a scratch.
抓抓抓 你就知道个抓
Do you know anything else?
你还会些别的吗
Can't you be soft on them?
你对他们就不能心慈手软
Principal Cai, what do you want?
蔡校长 您千什么
It's embarrassing for your subordinates.
您让下属很为难呀
Principal Cai, principal Cai
蔡校长 蔡校长
Don't make it difficult for your subordinates.
您不要让属下难做
Why did you give up?
你干什么 撒手
He
总监他
Have to go in.
非要进去
Go down.
下去下去
be
是
Cai Yuanpei
蔡元培
How dare you come here?
你还好意思来这儿
I mean, what do you do?
我说你是怎么管
what's up
干什么
Principal Cai, what can I do for you?
蔡校长 您有何贵干哪
Yes, I am. For which?
我是 我是为那个
Thirty-two students were arrested.
被抓的三十二名学生来的
I would like to invite the metropolitan police department
我愿请京师警察厅
Juntongling gate
步军统领门
Let my students go.
能放了我的学生
I'll take all the responsibility from Cai Yuanpei.
一切责任 我蔡元培来承担
You still want to release people?
你还想放人
I think I should arrest you too.
我觉得应该连你一起抓喽
If I let my students go
如果放了我的学生
You can arrest me.
你们可以抓我
Principal Cai, you are exaggerating.
蔡校长 你言重了
Where are the two of us?
我们二位呢
Today, I was trained by President Xu Da.
今天是受到了徐大总统的训
be in a bad mood
心情不好
Don't take it seriously.
你不要当真
But this arrest and release
不过这个抓人和放人
It's not our function.
不是我们的职权哪
We're just errands.
我们只是个跑腿的
Unless there is a warrant from the president.
除非有大总统的手令才是
The director, President Xu Da.
吴总监 徐大总统那儿
I must go to see him.
我必然要去见他
And I will never embarrass you two.
我也绝不会让二位为难
Just tonight.
只是今天晚上
I would like to ask you two to do me a favor.
我想请二位行个方便
Let me take my classmates back tonight.
让我今天晚上把同学们带回去
I must see President Xu Da tomorrow.
明天我一定去见徐大总统
Even if I offered to resign
哪怕是我提出辞职
At the same time.
也在所不惜
You are still the president of Peking University.
笑话亏你还是北大的校长呢
See the laws of the country as a joke.
视国家的法度如儿戏呀
Let people laugh.
放人 笑话
These students of yours
你的这些学生
Now he is a prisoner of the state.
现在是国家的犯人
Two places
二位
I am Cai Yuanpei, a teacher.
我蔡元培是个教书人
Now my students are in trouble.
如今我的学生遇了难
I should save each other.
我理应相救
Should come to care.
理应来关爱
So I'd like to invite two officers
所以我愿请二位长官
Can give me Cai Yuanpei's help
能给予我蔡元培帮助
Are the two officers?
难道二位长官
No child has ever been to school or studied.
就没有孩子上过学堂念过书
Li Tongling said that the students were prisoners.
李统领说学生们是犯人
I would like to ask
我想请问
Do students act for themselves?
学生们的行动是为了他们自己吗
They are patriotic.
他们是爱国呀
They are for that.
他们是为了那个
Unequal Paris Peace Treaty
不平等的巴黎和约
This unequal Paris peace treaty
这个不平等的巴黎和约
Aroused the anger of every Chinese.
激起了每一个中国人的愤怒
You two
你们二位
Are public officials in the government of the Republic of China.
都是在民国政府里面的公职人员
In your eyes
在你们的眼里
Patriotic students turned out to be prisoners
爱国的学生竟然成犯人
Ping the meaning of President Cai.
阶平 那个蔡校长的意思
No, you can't tell me.
对不对 你跟我说不着
Cai Yuanpei
蔡元培
They say you're a tiger's ass.
都说你是老虎的屁股摸不得
I'm going to kill you today.
我今天就要杀杀你的威风
Let you know what the rules are.
让你知道什么是规矩
Somebody get out of here!
来人 给我轰出去
Her students are just looking for trouble
他的学生就是寻滋事
Do wrong.
为非作
Catch what you should catch and kill what I should kill.
该抓的抓 我该杀的杀
Let him go down and have a rest.
让他下去休息 休息休息
I can't cure you.
治不了你们了
Principal Cai, you have seen it.
蔡校长 你也看到了
only if
除非
There are orders from President Xu Da.
有徐大总统的命令
otherwise
否则
There's really nothing we can do.
我们真的无能为力哪
take one's time in reaching a decision
从长计议
Director Wu
吴总监
What? This is
什么呀这是
China is Chinese.
中国是中国人的中国
You are also Chinese.
你们也是中国人
We marched in the streets for China.
我们上街游行是为了中国
What's wrong with us?
对我们有什么错
We are trying to make the government
我们是为了让政府
Refuse to sign the Paris Peace Treaty
拒签巴黎和约
Shandong is gone.
山东要没了
Is China still there?
中国还在吗
That's right.
对  对啊
Independence or death.
不独立 毋宁死
I would rather die than be independent.
不独立 宁死
Be quiet. This is a prison.
安静点 这儿是监狱
No matter how you are out there
不管你们在外边怎么样
Here
到这儿
You have to follow the rules here.
就得遵守这儿的规矩
Prisoners are not allowed to talk and play with each other.
收监犯人不许相互说话 嬉闹
When sleeping
睡觉时
Everyone must have a haircut every half hour.
每人必须每半小时一次头
Turn over
翻一次身
To prove that the prisoner is still alive
以证明犯人还活着
Prisoners can pee in the urinal.
犯人可以到尿桶小便
The stool must be silly.
大便则必须憨着
This is a violation of our human rights.
这是侵犯我们的人权
You have to follow the rules here.
就得遵守这儿的规矩
Wait until noon the next day when the fresh air.
等到第二天中午放风的时候
Can shit
才能大便
You are violating our human rights.
你们这是在侵犯我们的人权
I want to protest.
我要抗议
Yes, we want to protest.
对我们要抗议
Protest protest
抗议 抗议 抗议
Although you protest.
你们尽管抗议
But the rules must be enforced.
但规矩必须执行
Do you like to eat this thing?
这东西爱吃不吃
You have to listen to us here.
到这儿就得听我们的
Do you still have humanity?
你们还有人性吗
Isn't this bullying?
这不是欺负人吗
Is that they set fire to it without authorization.
就是他们几个擅自放火
Burn Zhao Jialou.
烧了赵家楼
Disrupt the plan
打乱了计划
Yes, it's their personal behavior.
没错 是他们的个人行为
Fu Sinian classmate
傅斯年同学
I think what happened today
我觉得今天的事情
You must take full responsibility.
你必须负全责
Can I take full responsibility for this?
我负得了这个全责吗
I didn't agree to go to Zhao Jialou.
我本来就不同意去赵家楼
But when?
可那个时候
Who listens to me as the commander in chief?
有谁听我这个总指挥的呀
Since no one listens to you as the commander in chief.
既然没有人听你这个总指挥的
Then I suggest
那我提议
Revoke the post of commander-in-chief Fu Sinian.
撤销傅斯年总指挥的职务
I agree, I agree, I agree
我同意 我同意我同意
good
好
I quit this commander in chief.
大
Don't do it
不干就不干
If you don't have money, you won't have it.
不千就不于
Let's re-elect now.
我们现在就重选
Don't go. It's not your fault.
你别走这不是你的错
Needless to say
不必多说
Boys and girls, I propose
同学们 我提议
In order to strengthen
为了加强
Organization and leadership of the student movement
对学生运动的组织和领导
Facilitate the communication between schools in Beijing.
便于京各个学校间的联络
Should be established.
应当立成立
Beijing College Student Affairs Association
北京大学生学生干事会
I agree, I agree, I agree
我同意 我同意 同意
Okay, it's an emergency. No choice
好 情况紧急 不选了
Directly by Deng Zhongxia Huangrikui Zhang Guotao
直接由邓中夏 黄日葵张国焘
Kang Baiqing Chen Baohao has five people.
康白情 陈宝号五人
For a thousand things.
为千事会的事
Be an officer of the office.
为干事会的干事
Raise your hand if you agree.
为千事会的千事
Agreed, agreed, agreed
同意同意 同意
pass
通过
Will the classmates come to the meeting.
事会的同学来开会
big
大
Take a look.
你们看一下
Try my best to rescue the arrested classmates.
全力营救被捕的同学
Students, students, students
同学们同学们同学们
Listen to me.
听我说
Mr Cai's negotiation with Wu Bingxiang is invalid.
蔡先生与吴炳湘交涉无效
Has returned to school from the metropolitan police department.
已从京师警察厅回到学校了
I'm on the phone right now.
此刻正在打电话
Contact principals of various schools in Beijing.
联络北京各个学校校长
Go to Peking University for a meeting tomorrow
明日到北大开会
Discuss the rescue of the arrested students.
共商营救被捕学生之事
What should I do?
怎么办啊
Jialun jialun
家伦家伦
Mid-summer, mid-summer
中夏 中夏
All the students from normal universities flocked to the playground.
高师的同学全部涌到操场上
Call unanimously for a strike.
一致要求实行罢课
Rescue the arrested classmates
营救被捕同学
I suggest Peking University take the lead.
我建议由北大牵头
Contact Beijing universities urgently.
紧急联系北京高校
Implement a general strike
实行总罢课
Okay, add it.
好加进去
Here, add this one.
来把这条加进去
This class can't be attended.
这课不能上了
Yes, no problem.
可以可以 没问题
Then I announced it.
那我宣布了
Okay, okay, announce it, announce it
好行行 宣布宣布
Students, students
同学们 同学们
Be quiet and listen to me.
安静一下  听我说
Upon urgent consultation by the Student Affairs Council.
经学生干事会紧急商决定
Please take action at once.
请全校同学立刻行动起来
In the name of the North University Students' Thousand Events Association
以北大学生千事会的名义
Contact Beijing No.14 Institute urgently.
紧急联络北京十四所
Secondary school or above
中等以上学校
A meeting will be held at Peking University at 9: 00 tomorrow morning.
于明日上午九时在北大开会
Negotiate and set up
协商并成立
Fourteen secondary and above schools in Beijing
北京十四所中等以上学校
students'federation
学生联合会
And strive to promote a resolution
并力争促成以决议
To rescue the arrested students.
全力营救被捕同学
All schools are on strike.
所有学校一律罢课
Until the arrested students return to school.
直至被捕同学回校为止
Urge principals to negotiate with the government.
敦促各校校长与政府交涉
Bail out the arrested students
保释营救被捕同学
Joint petition government
联合上书政府
Demand the punishment of traitors.
要求惩办卖国贼
Cao Rulin Zhang Zongxiang
曹汝霖 陆宗舆 章宗祥
4. Call our special envoy in Paris.
四 致电我国在巴黎的专使
Fight to the death for the Qingdao issue.
对于青岛问题要死力抗争
Never sign
决勿签字
Wudiantong National Education Association Chamber of Commerce
五通电全国教育会 商会
To action
致行动
Do you have any objections?
大家有什么异议吗
not have
没有
If there is no objection, please act immediately.
没有异议 请大家立刻行动
Let's go, let's go.
出发 行动 行动
have a walk
走走
Shouchang, when did we meet?
守常我们什么时候认识的
In Japan in 1915, right?
一九一五年在日本吧
Because of your "patriotism and self-awareness"
因为你的那个 《爱国心和自觉心》
Be besieged
被围攻
We had a long talk.
咱们俩长谈了一次
Yeah, that's why I'm conscious.
是啊就是为了这个自觉心
I went back to China to run New Youth.
回国我办了《新青年》
Because I saw your New Youth.
就是因为看了你的 《新青年》
Eliminates the misunderstanding to you.
消除了对你的误会
To join your camp.
才加入到了你的阵营
New Youth has been running for almost four years.
《新青年》办了快四年了
I feel
我感觉
It has reached a real turning point today.
今天它到了一个真正的转折点
I have a hunch that today
我预感今天
It will be a big day in Chinese history.
将会是中国历史上的一个大日子
It's from today.
是从今天起
We should not only shout.
我们不光要呐喊
It's even more important to take practical actions.
更要付出实际的行动了
Shouchang, I have a question for you
守常手 我有个问题想问你
You said
你说
When I started New Youth
创办 《新青年》 的时候
I put forward a goal.
我提出过一个目标
To find a truth for China
要为中国寻找一个真理
A road
一条道路
I want to ask you
我想问你
Did you find it today?
今天你找到了吗
I think I found it.
我觉得我找到了
Truth is Marxism.
真理就是马克思主义
The road is the Russian October Revolution.
道路就是俄国十月革命
Are you sure?
你确定吗
In the process of being determined.
正在确定的过程当中
中富兄
仲甫兄
I recently wrote an article.
我最近写了一篇
My View of Marxism
《我的马克思主义观》
Want to publish it in New Youth.
想在《新青年》 发表
Are you okay with that?
你没意见吧
Of course, I started from the second half of last year
当然 我从去年下半年
Pay close attention to Marx's works.
就十分关注马克思的著作
First half of this year
今年上半年
Every issue of New Youth is published and introduced.
《新青年》每期都刊登和介绍
Marxist articles
马克思主义的文章
Especially last month's Weekly Review.
特别是上个月的《每周评论》
Published Marx's
刊登了马克思的
Chapter II of the Communist Manifesto
《共产党宣言》 第二章
Have a great response.
很有反响
My thoughts also touched me a lot.
我的思想也触动很大
Manifesto of the Communist Party
《共产党宣言》
It is a classic work of Marx and Engels.
是马克思和恩格斯的经典著作
Very wonderful and profound.
非常精彩深刻
I can recite many paragraphs.
很多段落我都能背
To be honest.
老实说
Although I'm not as sure as you are.
我虽然没有像你那么确认
But my interest in Marxism
但是我对马克思主义的兴趣
It's getting stronger and stronger
越来越浓烈了
As for the October Revolution in Russia and China
至于说俄我国的十月革命
I feel the same way.
我也有同感
I didn't do much research.
我研究得不多
But I think
但是我觉得
Compared with Britain, France and America
跟英法美比起来
The Russian way is more suitable for China.
可能俄国的方式更适合中国
Shouchang, I really want to have a chance to have time
守常 我非常想 有机会有时间
The two of us carefully and well
我们两个仔细地好好地
Discuss this problem.
讨论一下这个问题
I also have a lot of ideas and questions.
我也有很多的想法和问题
I want to discuss with you
想跟你讨论
Things happen today.
今天一天事情发生下来
It's very exciting for me.
对我刺激很大
I'm thinking.
我在想
Maybe from today.
可能从今天起
We're going to take a road together.
我们要一起走上一条
The road of direct confrontation with the reactionary government
和反动政府直接对抗的道路
Shouchang
守常
How do you think this road should go?
你想这条路应该怎么走
Actually, I've been thinking about it for a long time
其实我想了很久
I think what you said is right.
我觉得你说的是对的
We have to let the people
我们必须要让民众
Come out and solve the problem directly.
直接出来解决问题
We students alone can't do it.
光靠我们学生不行
We must mobilize the masses to fight.
我们必须要发动群众进行斗争
Yeah, today was just a trigger.
对 今天只是一个导火索
Our mission
我们的任务
Is to use it to detonate the whole of China.
是要用它引爆整个中国
Let all walks of life in the country take action.
让全国各行各业都要行动起来
Get them directly involved.
让他们直接参与到
In the struggle to transform the whole society.
改造整个社会的斗争中来
Only this China has hope.
唯此 中国才有希望
Our past "New Youth"
过去咱们的《新青年》
Just focus on ideological enlightenment.
只是关注思想启蒙
Now we have to make it clear that
现在我们要明确提出
The task of fundamentally transforming society
从根本上改造社会的任务
This is our responsibility.
这就是我们的责任
good
好
Our weekly review.
那我们的《每周评论》
And New Youth.
和《新青年》
Two publications
两个刊物
Do more articles in this area.
要多做这方面的文章
We will start tonight.
今天晚上我们就开始
Try to get out tomorrow.
争取明天出
中富兄
仲甫兄
You remind me of that sentence again.
你又让我想起了那句话
Let the storm come more violent.
让暴风雨来得更猛烈些吧
go
走
To maintain order and rectify the style of study.
本部为维持秩序 整顿学风
All schools are ordered to strictly investigate May 4th.
特通令各校严查五月四日
Fire in Zhao Jialou
火烧赵家楼事件
To the student who caused the trouble.
对为首滋事的学生
Dismissal
一律开除
Not appealable
不可姑息
That is, follow
仰即遵照
This order
此令
What do you mean?
什么意思
They don't have to be fired.
不用他们开除
We can't learn this.
这学咱们不上了
I can't get on. I can't get on
不上了不上了
Strike, strike, strike
罢课罢课罢课
ladies and gentlemen
诸位
Great sages gathered in our metropolitan police department.
厂
It's really flattering.
真是蓬苹生辉牙
Please come inside, please.
里边请 里边请 来来来
I don't know what you have in mind.
不知各位有何贵哪
Dear Director Hao
尊敬的昊总监
We are all principals of major schools in Beijing.
我们都是北京各大学校的校长
We're all here for bail today.
今天我们都是为了保释
Thirty-two students who were arrested came.
那被抓捕的三十二名学生而来
Director Hao, please grant permission.
请昊总监恩准
Principal Cai, you were immediately dismissed.
蔡校长 您都马上被撤职了
How can you care about the students?
怎么还管学生的事啊
You will not be dismissed.
你撤职不撤职
It doesn't really matter.
这倒没有什么关系
These students
这些学生
She will always be my Cai Yuanpei's student.
他永远是我蔡元培的学生
Besides, the behavior of students marching in the streets
况且 学生上街游行的行为
He's not unreasonable.
他并非是无理取筛
Is not looking for trouble.
并非是寻滋事
He did it for the unequal Paris Peace Treaty.
他是为了不平等的巴黎和约
And marched on the streets.
而上街游行
We support their actions.
他们的行动我们是支持的
If you want to be held accountable
如果要追究责任
Then pursue us.
那就追究我们好了
Director Wu
吴总监
As long as you release the arrested classmates
只要您释放被捕的同学
Several of our principals will resign collectively.
我们几位校长将集体辞职
To resign collectively.
对集体辞职
resign (office/one's job/post)
辞职
President Chen
陈大校长
It's none of my business whether you resign or not.
您辞职不辞职不干我事啊
This thing about releasing students.
这释放学生的事情啊
It's not really under the authority.
确实不是在下的权限
I can't be the master.
我做不了主啊
at this point
这一点
I last night.
我昨天晚上
President Cai has made it clear.
和蔡校长已经说得明明白白的
I hope you, Dae-hyun
希望各位大贤
Don't embarrass me
莫使在下为难哪
Director Wu
吴总监
Now all schools in Beijing will start a general strike.
现在北京各校均要开始总罢课了
It is these arrested students who are the cause.
起因就是这些被捕的学生
If things get too big
如果事情闹大了
The consequences are unimaginable.
后果是不堪设想啊
Especially you.
特别是您
Shoulder the general responsibility of social security in the capital.
肩负的是京师社会治安的总任
You should think twice.
您可要三思啊
I thank you for reminding me.
我谢谢您的提醒
Great sages all know.
诸位大贤都知道
You are a guest of a high-ranking political official.
您是政界高官的座上客
Let me remind you, too.
我也给您提个醒
You say
您说
As long as you can stay with President Xu.
只要你能在徐大总统那儿
Ask for a warrant
讨来一纸手令
Brother, how about releasing people immediately?
兄弟立马放人 怎么样
Can you bend the rules?
那能不能通融一下
Don't do that
要不这样
You let us do student work.
您放人 我们去做学生的工作
Right.-Right
对-对
You release people.
您放人
Let's do student work.
我们去做学生的工作
I said, gentlemen, gentlemen
我说诸位 诸位
This is the police department.
这是警察厅啊
It's not a vegetable market
又不是菜市场
How can you bargain?
何来的讨价还价呢
I understand your feelings.
诸位的心情我都理解
I'm just sick. I'm in a hospital.
只是有病乱投医
Wrong temple gate
走错了庙门
I advise you to find Xu Shichang.
我劝诸位还是去找徐世昌吧
I'm busy with business.
在下公务繁忙
Please go back, please go back.
请回吧 请回吧
If you big sages insist on not leaving.
如果诸位大贤执意不肯走的话
Folk prescription for tea
偏房喝茶啊
Make tea, make tea
沏茶沏茶
Gentlemen, please.
诸位请
wait a moment
且慢
Brother Tan, please stay.
镜潭兄请留步
It turns out that the fellow villagers have arrived.
原来是老乡驾到了
Lose one's welcome
有失远迎
Forgive me, forgive me, forgive me.
见谅见谅见谅
We are from the same town but different departments.
咱俩同乡不同系
Two cars on the road.
两股道上的车
I dare not climb high.
我不敢高攀哪
Chairman Wang is here.
那汪委员长大驾光临
What instructions?
有何训示
Let's talk inside.
咱们里边说
Say it right here.
就在这儿说
I'm here to submit a bail submission.
我是来递交保释呈文的
Who are you bailing out?
您要保释谁呀
Me and Wang Chonghui Lin Changmin.
我和王宠惠 林长民三人
Bail 32 students arrested jointly.
联名保释被捕的三十二名学生
This is a bail petition.
这是保释呈文
Let me read it to you.
我念给你听听
No, I'll see for myself
不用了 我自己看吧
Wu Bingxiang
吴炳湘
Are you going to listen or not?
你到底是听还是不听
I listen
我听
listen to
听
I'm all ears.
我洗耳恭听
Steal the fourth day of this month
窃本月四日
Students from various schools in Beijing
北京各校学生
Call for diplomatic issues
为外交问题奔走呼号
The gathering of people led to the brewing incident
聚众之下 致酿事变
In the noisy field at that time
当时喧扰场中
More than 30 students were arrested.
学生被捕者三十余人
Stimulate the nation into excesses.
国民为国 激成过举
It's sad.
其情可哀
And this more than 30 people
而此三十余人者
Not necessarily the person who caused the accident.
未必即为肇事之人
Wait for Date to be released on bail first.
大等特先愿交保释放
If you need to interrogate in the future
以后如需审问
That is to say, the case is delivered by the big guarantee.
即由大等担保送案不误
It's hard to know how exciting things are.
群情激动 事变更不可知
For this reason, it is urgent to be frank.
为此迫切直陈 即气准保
Fortunately for the people.
国民幸甚
Present to the police chief
呈警察总监
Chengren
具呈人
Wang Dawei
汪大燮
Wang Chonghui
王宠惠
Lin Changmin
林长民
Chairman Wang
汪委员长
I'll take your bail submission.
您的保释呈文我收下了
Just you guys!
只是诸位呀
This release of students
这释放学生一事
There must also be the approval of President Xu Da.
还得有徐大总统的批文哪
I hope you can understand my difficulties.
希望诸位能理解在下的苦衷啊
Sell newspapers
卖报卖报
See Beijing academic circles calling the Chinese delegation in Paris
看北京学界致电巴黎中国代表团
Please do not sign in humiliation.
愿请万勿屈辱签字
Please sign without humiliation.
悬请方勿屈辱签字
Sell newspapers
卖报 卖报
See academic circles around the world calling Cai Yuanpei
看各地学界致电蔡元培
Solidarity with Peking University Students Movement
声援北大学生运动
Read the newspaper
看报看报
See Beijing academic circles calling the Chinese representative in Paris
看北京学界致电巴黎中国代表
Please do not sign in humiliation.
愿请勿屈辱签字
Come and see, come and buy.
快来看 快来买呀
What's your name?
你叫什么
Xu de
许德
How old are you?
多大了
Twenty-nine
二十九
Is also a great person!
也是大好年华的人哪
How can you commit murder and arson?
怎么能于出杀人放火的勾当啊
What we did was patriotic.
我们干的可都是爱国的行为
It's not murder and arson.
不是杀人放火的勾当
love one's country
爱国
Are you so patriotic?
有你这样爱国的吗
Xu Deheng
许德珩
I just want to ask you one question.
我就想问你一句啊
You marched in the streets.
你们上街游行
Who is behind your boss?
谁是你们的幕后指使人呢
My head grows on my shoulder.
我的脑袋长在自己的肩膀上
Do I need to be instructed by others?
我用得着受别人指使吗
How did I hear?
我怎么听说
你是李大钊
你是李大钊
Chen Duxiu's loyal followers
陈独秀的忠实信徒啊
come on
来吧
Have a glass of water first.
先喝一杯水吧
Tell me about it
给我说说
What have they told you recently?
他们最近都跟你们说了些什么
Come and drink
来喝
Director Wu
吴总监
You flatter me.
您高抬我了
He, Chen Duxiu, is a famous scholar in China.
他陈独秀是全国闻名的大学者
Li Dazhao is the director of the library.
李大钊是图书馆的主任
I am just an ordinary student.
我就是一普通学生
I can't even meet them at ordinary times.
我跟他们平时连面都见不到
How do you know what they said?
怎么知道他们说了些什么
Xu De, you know
许德 你要知道
I came to ask you myself today.
我今天亲自来问你
Is to give you an open hand.
就是要给你一条生路
Why don't you cooperate?
你怎么不配合呀
I really want to cooperate with you, Director Wu.
我是真的想配合您 吴总监
So what I just said is true.
所以我刚才说的都是实话
You can't let me tell lies.
您总不能让我说假话
Come and cooperate with you.
来跟您配合吧
Take out
带出去
be
是
Come in
进来吧
What are you asking?
都问出些什么来
These students are all in cahoots.
这些学生都是串通好的
Confessions are all the same.
供词全都一样
Interrogate all night
通宵审问
Be sure to dig out the mastermind behind it.
务必挖出幕后指使人
be
是
The situation has changed dramatically since May 5th.
自五月五日来 风云突变
Beijing National Foreign Affairs Association Chamber of Commerce Farmers Association
北京国民外交协会 商会 农会
All sent letters to the government and sent electricity to the whole country.
均致信政府并通电全国
Support the student movement
支持学生运动
Request the release of the arrested students.
要求释放被捕学生
Southern government Sun Wen Linsen Tang Shaoyi
南方政府孙文 林森 唐绍仪
And Kang Youwei, Wu Peifu and Zhang Jingyao.
以及康有为 吴佩孚 张敬尧
Chen Guangyuan and others expressed their support for the students.
陈光远等均表示支持学生
Ask Cao Rulin Zhang Zongxiang to remove Lu Zongyu.
要求罢免曹汝霖 章宗祥 陆宗舆
There are several senators in Congress.
国会议员中有数名参议员
Have jointly sent a letter to the President.
已联名致信大总统
Request the release of the arrested students.
要求释放被捕学生
Except Beijing and Guangzhou
除北京广州外
Shanghai
上海
Nanjing
南京
Tianjin
天津
Wuhan
武汉
Changsha
长沙
Activities in support of Beijing students also took place.
也都发生了声援北京学生的活动
In the last two days
近两日来
Presidential Palace and State Council
总统府和国务院
Received a message of solidarity with Beijing.
收到声援北京活动的电文
More than one hundred copies
一百多份
Solidarity activities around the world show the following characteristics
各地声援活动呈现下列特征
Set up student organizations
成立学生组织
To be responsible for implementing various action plans.
以负责实现各项行动计划
Organize demonstrations
组织示威游行
To protest the government's foreign policy.
以抗议政府的外交政策
Paris Peace Treaty and Arrest Students
巴黎和约和逮捕学生
3. Completely boycott Japanese goods.
三 全面抵制日货
All these indicate that
这些都表明
The government's crisis of trust has taken shape in an all-round way.
政府的信任危机已全面形成
All right, all right, let's not talk about it
好了好了 不说这些了
Let's see.
大家看看
What countermeasures should we take?
我们应该采取什么对策吧
president
大总统
This is my third resignation.
这是我第三次上递的辞呈
I'm really incompetent.
我实在难以胜任
Please approve
请您批准
Fu Zengxiang, this is not your resignation.
傅增湘 你这不是辞呈
This is blackmail.
你这是要挟
At this time, you have to pick a fault.
在这个时候你要挑子不干
No way.
门儿都没有
No, you can resign.
不辞职也可以
Then release the arrested students.
那就放了被捕的学生
Students have been on strike for two days.
学生罢课已经两天了
Continue to develop.
再发展下去
The situation will be unmanageable.
局面将无法收拾
impossible
不行
Duan Dashuai said that students can't play it.
段大帅说了 学生不能放
Cao Rulin can't go either.
曹汝霖也不能走
I don't believe it.
我就不信了
We have guns in our hands.
我们手里有枪
Let every student turn the sky upside down?
还让凡个学生把天翻了不成
Who says students can't be proud?
谁说学生不能翻天呀
This Beijing city
这北京城
Has been turned upside down by students.
已经被学生闹得天翻地覆了
Do you know what the students below are going to do?
你知道下边学生到底要干什么吗
They intend to launch a general mobilization to the whole society.
他们打算向全社会发起总动员
The newly established Beijing Federation of Students
刚刚成立的北京学联
They are going to the streets.
他们打算上街
Go to the street club factory to give a speech.
到街头社团 工厂去演讲
I also plan to go to Shanghai, Wuhan, Changsha and other places.
还打算到上海 武汉 长沙等地
Give a speech
进行演说
Organize the National Federation of Students.
策划组织全国学联
Now it's not just academia.
现在不仅仅是学界
They also encouraged the business community.
商界也被他们鼓动起来了
Seeing that the military community is also dividing.
眼看着军界也在分化
Wait until May 7th.
等到五月七日
As soon as the Central Park National Convention opens
中央公园国民大会一开
It must be a volcanic eruption.
必定是一座座火山爆发
until this moment
到那个时候
There's nothing you can do to help.
你就是再有辙也无济于事了
Director Wu
吴总监
Have you listened to the dangerous words?
危言箕听了吧
president
大总统
I'm Wu Bingxiang's alarmist.
我吴炳湘是不是危言箕听
Please listen to the Prime Minister's opinion.
您听听总理的意见吧
Premier Qian
钱总理
Are you so pessimistic?
你也这么悲观吗
My opinion
我的看法
Even worse than Director Hao.
比昊总监有过之而无不及
such being the case
既然如此
What's your police chief's strategy?
你这个警察总监有什么对策呀
My response is only one.
我的对策只有一个
Is to release the arrested students.
就是释放被捕的学生
Doesn't releasing students hit themselves in the face?
释放学生不是自己打自己的脸吗
Besides, what about the old section?
再说了 老段那儿怎么交代
president
大总统
I only mean the release of students.
我的意思只有释放学生这一条
If you must not let it go.
如果你一定不放的话
If there is any trouble in Beijing again
北京要是再闹出什么乱子来
I'm irresponsible.
我可不负责任
I also resign.
我也辞职
Jingtan
镜潭
What kind of childish behavior does Jing Tan play?
镜潭 耍什么小孩子脾气哟
you come back
你回来
Come back and sit down.
回来回来 坐下啊
Premier Qian, you are the Premier of the State.
钱总理 你是国务总理
What do you think you should do?
你说应该怎么办
My opinion
我的看法
Exactly the same as Director Wu.
和吴总监完全一致
good
好
Since you are all in this opinion.
既然你们都是这个意见
I can agree to release the students.
我可以同意释放学生
But I have asked you to stay at two o'clock.
但是我有两点请你们住了
First, make sure that all schools
第一 确保所有学校
Classes must resume on May 7th.
五月七日必须复课
The second stone is to ensure that all students and teachers
第二石 确保所有学生和老师
May 7th will not be allowed to participate.
五月七日一律不得参加
Central Park National Congress
中央公园国民大会
If anything goes wrong, I'll ask you.
如有差池 我拿你们是问
Go ahead with the discussion.
你们继续议吧
Students!
诸位学子
In response to appeals from all walks of life
应社会各界的呼吁请求
With great kindness, the president
大总统以仁厚之心
Order to forgive you for your recklessness.
下令宽恕各位的鲁莽之举
Our hall will also send a car to take you back to school.
本厅也将派车送你们归校
I hope you can be grateful to the government.
希望各位能够感恩政府
Peace of mind to study and stop making trouble.
安心学习 别再闹事
Please
请吧
Fellow students
各位学子
The headmaster of Ji personally picked you up.
祭校长亲自接你们来了
Please
请吧
Mr. Cai
蔡先生
中富先生
仲甫先生
Director Wu
吴总监
it is easier to invite sb in than to send him away
请神容易送神难
We are very clear.
我们十分清楚
I'll wait for the students to be detained here for one more day.
我等学生在这里多被拘留一天
One more day to stimulate the people.
对国民就多刺激一天
If I wait for 32 people.
尚若我等三十二人
Killed by Jieer, etc.
皆被尔等所杀
It can wake up 400 million people in China.
可以惊醒全中国四万万的人民
We're not leaving.
我们不走
We're going to put you in jail.
我们要把你这个牢底坐穿
Wear the base firmly.
对把牢底坐穿
Sit through the prison floor
把牢底坐穿
Look at principal Cai.
蔡校长 您瞧瞧
What's this about?
这叫怎么回事啊
Your spirit
你们的精神
I admire Cai Yuanpei very much
我蔡元培十分敬佩
But I want to tell my classmates.
但是我要告诉同学们
In order to rescue you
为了营救你们出
Teachers and students in many schools in Beijing
北京很多学校的师生
Have made great sacrifices.
都做出了巨大的牺牲
Schools will resume classes today.
今天各个学校就要复课了
Everyone is eager to see it through.
大家都望眼欲穿地
Looking forward to your safe return to school.
期盼着你们能平安地回到学校
Students, don't let down.
同学们千万不要辜负了
Hundreds of thousands of teachers and students in Beijing
北京十几万师生
To your sincere heart!
对你们的真诚之心哪
Mr. Cai, you don't have to persuade us.
蔡先生 您不用再劝我们了
We appreciate your help.
我们很感激大家的救助
I also yearn for a free life outside prison.
也向往牢狱外自由的生活
As long as it can awaken the Chinese people
只要能唤醒中国的民众
Even if we give our lives
我们哪怕付出生命
I'm willing to do my best.
也在所不辞
you
你们
It's really
可真是
It's not just arrogance.
不是一般的自大呀
You think
你们以为
Wake up a
唤醒一个
Feudal thought
被封建思想
A nation that has been banned for thousands of years
禁了几千年的民族
Is it that easy?
是那么容易的吗
You think
你们以为
To wipe out our nation.
要扫除我们这个民族
Numbness and indifference in the blood
血液里面的麻木冷漠
Inertial thinking
惰性思维
Is it a day's work?
是一日之功吗
It will take several generations.
那是要经过几代人
Strive for a great cause
努力奋斗的大事业
Let me tell you something.
我告诉你们
You have no right to die now.
你们现在没有权利去死
Our disaster-stricken country
我们这个灾难深重的国家
You need to live.
需要你们去活着
You need to fight.
需要你们去奋斗
中富先生
仲甫先生
We'll go with you.
我们跟你们走
So this is how you brought them back.
原来你是这样给他们带回来的
It's your style
倒是你的风格
But sometimes you can be a bit bossy.
不过有的时候你实在是有点霸道
Am I overbearing
我霸道吗
I'm not overbearing.
不是我霸道
They are too confused.
是他们太糊涂
revolutionary
革命者
How can you do something that kills yourself in the revolution?
怎么能做自绝于革命的事情
What about your alarm clock?
那你这个闹钟
You have to respect the bomb rejection, too.
也得尊重一下炸弹的决绝吧
What do you mean?
什么意思
For example.
打个比方啊
On a piece of land
一片大地上
Lying a group of sleeping people.
躺着一群沉睡的人
The volcano is in the distance.
远处就是火山
It's about to explode.
马上就要爆发了
You are like an alarm clock.
你就像个闹钟
Facing these sleeping people
面对这些沉睡的人
You want to wake them up?
你想把他们叫醒
You keep ringing.
你持续不断地响着
Some people who sleep lightly.
有的睡得浅的人
You woke me up.
被你叫醒了
Go with you to wake everyone up.
跟你一块去叫醒众人
But there are too many people.
但是人数太多了
Your voice is too weak.
你们的声音太微强
After all, there are limited people to wake up.
叫醒的人毕竟有限
And it's uneven.
而且保不齐
Some people are bored.
有的人嫌烦
From time to time, I also break two.
时不时还踢坏两个
Some alarm clocks are too late.
那么有的闹钟怕来不及
Take your own life.
就拿自己的生命
As raw material
当作原料
Turned into a bomb
化成了炸弹
It woke up a large number of people.
一下就炸醒了一大片人
Then, as you say.
那照你这么说
The bomb is much more powerful than the alarm clock.
炸弹要比闹钟厉害多了
Then just a few more bombs?
那么多来几个炸弹不就行了吗
What's the use of an alarm clock?
还要闹钟何用啊
No, yeah
非也呀
Brother Zhongfu, think about it
仲甫兄 你想想
Without the alarm clock
要是没有闹钟
Day and night, "the emperor screamed with painstaking efforts."
夜以继日「 呕心沥血地帝鸣
There will be no bomb.
便不会有炸弹的诞生
Although the bomb is powerful
炸弹的威力虽大
But it can't overcome people's inertia after all.
但是它终究战胜不了人之惰性啊
Only the sieve clock is needed.
只有需要筛钟
Keep reminding, keep watching.
持续不断地提醒看坚持看
To finally wake everyone up.
才能最终将所有人唤醒啊